

Maximilian Bernkopf

maximilian.bernkopf@gmail.com

maximilianbernkopf.github.io/data/

Maximilian Bernkopf

maximilianbernkopf

Coogle Scholar

Summary_

Max is pursuing his PhD in computational mathematics at the TU Wien focussing on the numerics of time-harmonic wave propagation problems. Besides mathematics, he is a true data nerd. He loves handling and visualizing big data sets and discovering the unique stories they can tell. His languages of choice are R and Python, depending on the task at hand. He gained his data science experience working at start-ups in Vienna, where he solved problems involving time series analysis and outlier detection.

Education

PhD Candidate in Computational Mathematics

TU WIEN

Vienna, Austria 09/2017-current

- Doctoral thesis: "Finite Element Analysis of the Heterogeneous Helmholtz Equation and Least Squares Methods"
- Supervisor: Prof. Jens Markus Melenk, PhD

Dipl.-Ing. (equivalent MSc) in Financial and Actuarial Mathematics

TU WIEN

Vienna, Austria 11/2015-06/2016

• Master thesis: "Analysis of the alpha-hypergeometric stochastic volatility model"

· Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Stefan Gerhold

BSc in Financial and Actuarial Mathematics

TIJ WIEN

INTRABASE

MANTIGMA

Internship

Vienna, Austria

Vienna, Austria

Matura (High school graduation equivalent)

SCHOTTENGYMNASIUM

10/2002-06/2010

Work Experience _____

Data Scientist Vienna, Austria

09/2016-09/2017

08/2016-09/2017

- Focus on statistical learning and outlier detection.
- Development of statistical algorithms for unsupervised outlier detection.
- · High dimensional anomaly detection of categorical and numerical data.

Data Scientist Vienna, Austria

· Focus on time series analysis and supervised learning.

- · Account balance forecasting for retail banking.
- Electricity demand forecasting utilizing classical mathematical time series models as well as novel deep learning techniques.
- · Machine learning based credit scoring models.

Research Assistant Vienna, Austria

TU WIEN, RESEARCH UNIT OF FINANCIAL AND ACTUARIAL MATHEMATICS

10/2015-06/2016

· Focus on credit risk models and their implementation.

Vienna, Austria

FMA FINANZMARKTAUFSICHT ÖSTERREICH • Focus on Solvency II.

09/2013-12/2013

Community Service / Paramedic

Vienna, Austria

ARBEITER-SAMARITER-BUND

12/2010-08/2011



R tidyverse (dplyr, ggplot2, tibble, purrr, readr etc.), dbplyr, data.table, shiny,

forecast, caret, tidymodels, plotly, rmarkdown

Python ngsolve, numpy, pandas, matplotlib, scipy, sklearn

Proficient in Matlab, Mapel, Mathematica, LaTex, git

Basic Knowledge of SQL, Hugo, C, C++, Java

Languages German (native), English (fluent), Russian (basic)

Operating System of Choice Linux + i3wm

Hobbies and Random Bits

Sports Calisthenics, Climbing, Bouldering, Gymnastics & Acrobatics

Dancing, Reading stoic philosophy, Non-modern Art, Listening to audiobooks at 2x the speed Non-athletic Hobbies

Less Usefull Skills Juggeling, Yoyo-tricks, Solving the Rubiks cube **Guilty Pleasures** Selfimporvement books, Reddit, Memes, Cheese

Random Facts Can fit at least three Soletti sideways in his mouth, Dyed his hair blond to be Son Goku for Halloween,

Google Local Guide Level 7, Weirdly enthusiastic about his Dyson

Teaching

Tutor - Analysis 1-3, Computer Mathematics

TU WIEN, INSTITUTE OF ANALYSIS AND SCIENTIFIC COMPUTING

Vienna, Austria

Seminar Instructor - Seminar on inverse problems

TU WIEN, INSTITUTE OF ANALYSIS AND SCIENTIFIC COMPUTING

03/2019-07/2019

Vienna, Austria

Vienna, Austria

2015-2021

Seminar Instructor - Seminar on uncertainty quantification and approximation theory of

neural networks

TU WIEN, INSTITUTE OF ANALYSIS AND SCIENTIFIC COMPUTING 10/2018-02/2019

Research Stays _____

Université Polytechnique Hauts-de-France

WORKING WITH PROF. DR. SERGE NICAISE

Universität Zürich

WORKING WITH PROF. DR. STEFAN SAUTER

Valenciennes, France

09/2020-12/2020

Zürich, Switzerland

09/2019-12/2019

Publications

Wavenumber-explicit stability and convergence analysis of hp Finite Element discretizations of Helmholtz problems in piecewise smooth media, in preparation

M. Bernkopf, T. Chaumont-Frelet, J. M. Melenk

Optimal convergence rates in L^2 for a first order system least squares finite element method. Part II: inhomogeneous boundary conditions, in preparation

M. Bernkopf, J. M. Melenk

Solvability of Discrete Helmholtz Equations, submitted

M. Bernkopf, S. Sauter, C. Torres, A. Veit

arXiv e-prints arXiv:2105.02273, 2021

Optimal convergence rates in L^2 for a first order system least squares finite element method. Part I: homogeneous boundary conditions, submitted

M. Bernkopf, J. M. Melenk

arXiv e-prints arXiv:2012.12919, 2020

Analysis of the hp-Version of a First Order System Least Squares Method for the Helmholtz Equation M. Bernkopf, J. M. Melenk

Advanced Finite Element Methods with Applications: Selected Papers from the 30th Chemnitz Finite Element Symposium 2017, 2019